<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vincenzo Coia</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Vincenzo Coia</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Vincenzo Coia</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/raw_testimonials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/raw_testimonials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;lee-2017&#34;&gt;Lee, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn started working with my 4 year-old son 5 years ago, who has ASD. Shawn established a rapport and an engaging relationship with him within a few sessions. Shawn coaches our son in areas that are challenging for him: specifically, social and contextual language skills; adaptability to changes; capability to stay on required agenda; and general developmental abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family (including our son&#39;s grandparents), his nanny and his teacher in school have observed significant improvements in various areas within the short 5 months. They were excited to &amp;ldquo;report&amp;rdquo; our son&#39;s openness and communication initiatives to me. Shawn takes a holistic approach in his work with our son and has become part of our family while maintaining his professionalism. He constantly thinks of ways to help our son and incorporates members of our family, teachers, and therapists in his approach so that our son has a consistently conducive environment in overcoming his challenges. In addition, Shawn exposes our son to everyday life situations with a firm and encouraging attitude so that our son is pushed appropriately to his learning potential with trust in &amp;ldquo;Shawn&#39;s way&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family is very fortunate to have Shawn on board in helping our son&#39;s development and we look forward to more positive changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;frost-2012&#34;&gt;Frost, 2012&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our son was diagnosed with ASD and (PDD-NOS)  at aged 2 and a half years old. Our son began showing more signs of autism and displayed challenging behaviours&amp;rsquo; that were too difficult for us to handle.​​​​​​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had hired several specialist that have worked with us over a period of 8 months,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is Shawn who has changed our lives. His outstanding skill at dealing with children who have special needs is like nothing I have seen before. He has been able to achieve with our son what no other specialist has. Through constructive play, patience and innovative ideas, Our son has made progress in all areas,  allowing Shawn to teach him different activities and develop the skills to bring him to age appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 2 weeks of working with Shawn, our son ran to the window and waited for Shawn&#39;s car to pull up. He then ran to the door, took Shawn&#39;s hand and pulled him downstairs to the therapy room without giving me a backward glance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn truly has a unique way in bringing out the best in children, all children. We have come to rely upon Shawn for helping us with our son in all aspects of day to day living with a child that has autism. His methods and common sense make life so much easier for all of us and we value him as a person as well as a professional in this field.​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bryan-9-years-old-2017&#34;&gt;Bryan, 9-years-old, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn is a person who is the author of Don&#39;t Tease Mr. Beeze. He teaches people with Autism. He is a nice personality. He has a godson which is twins named Freddie and Frankie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn has helped me with all subjects. My behavier was bad and now it is good. Example is autism. Shawn has helped me with shooting the basketball to the net the real way. Shawn helped me communicate in school with my teacher and friends. Shawn helped me play the guitar. Shawn has helped me taste fruits. Shawn has helped me play chess. Shawn has helped me play guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;noor-b-age-13-2016&#34;&gt;Noor B, Age 13, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn is a very socially understanding person who comforts people in their worst times. He is a great motivator and makes people feel good even when they are down. His jokes and pranks are uplifting and always makes my day better. Shawn is a man always serving others and helping those who need his help the most. He tends to work with those who suffer from mental illness over those who are just looking for a help; he understands his abilities can help those who need it most. Over the 6 years I&#39;ve known him, he has helped me with all social and academic issues that have come my way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn is one the most intelligent and kind hearted people I know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;r-banwait-age-12-2012&#34;&gt;R Banwait, Age 12, 2012&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Help, the word itself means assisting, but Shawn has done much more than that for me and my family. Shawn hasn&#39;t just helped me with my work, he has helped socially and mentally. Not only have I been getting straight A&#39;s, but I am now more comfortable around people and whenever there is problem at school, I know I can share with him and get good advice. Shawn is joy to  be mentored by and whenever my mother or father wants me to work on something a little bit or, academically or behaviour  wise, he is always there to help me to improve. Shawn has done a lot for me and I dearly thank him for everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;norman-7-years-old-2017&#34;&gt;Norman, 7-years-old, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Shawn, thanks for teaching me. I have learn alot from you. We had went to lot of diffrent resturants and places to enjoy over time. You are a great kind caring teacher. You are good at teaching. You always cheer me up when I am sad. I love being with you. You taght me how to play chess and taght me how to bike. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gill-2017&#34;&gt;Gill, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn began by assisting our, then 9-year-old son, who was displaying academic and behavioural challenges. Shawn implemented therapy and methods that helped our son progress rapidly during the first month. His teachers, peers and other family members noticed the change almost immediately. Our son&#39;s confidence skyrocketed and he was able to absorb new information willingly. His confidence, self-independence, and self-worth strengthened. It took less than a couple of months before our son no longer thought of himself as &amp;ldquo;the dumb one&amp;rdquo; amongst his peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Shawn&#39;s dedication, our son, now 16, is now attending one of the most prestigious schools, where he was one of a few who were selected out of hundreds. This accomplishment was due to his academic success, and his strong confidence to take on any task.​​​​​​​​​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn&#39;s extensive background in family relations helped counsel and guide our family through several personal crises. He provided a pro-active approach to problem solving with the family as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn isn&#39;t just our family specialist, he&#39;s now a member of our family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;k-taneja-age-16-2016&#34;&gt;K, Taneja, Age 16, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years ago my life changed; I met a man that was there to help me with my education and with my problems. Shawn not only helped with my studies, but also life lessons that will apply to me whenever I need them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn often said, &amp;ldquo;Relax, take your time and you will figure it out.&amp;rdquo; He always introduces a variety methods and how there are different resources that I can use. He has been an amazing toward me; leading me to the right decisions and wanting me to do well physically and mentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn is a very nice, polite and caring guy.  I am able to talk to him even if I have done something wrong so he could help me figure out the situation. He has been a mentor that I learn new things from everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to have him in my life as an amazing life instructor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;carol-2017&#34;&gt;Carol, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn, &amp;ldquo;I&#39;d like to thank you for all your work done with him so far and your advice. He is much better, calmer and emotionally stronger.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mother-of-a-5-year-old-daughter-2011&#34;&gt;Mother of a 5-year-old daughter, 2011&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are a gifted child whisperer. I want you to know that a miraculous change happens when (my daughter) sees you. The difference is like night and day. I am so thankful (my daughter) has you&amp;hellip; you help her to free herself from her bonds and step into harmony and beauty. The peace she experiences is visible. Words will never capture the depth of my gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;logan-2016&#34;&gt;Logan 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From our first conversation on the phone I felt Shawn had the capability to ask the right questions and made me feel at ease. During our first meeting, I was also very impressed with how he handled our son who is very selective with people&amp;hellip; we now have a much happier child&amp;hellip;since our first session 7 months ago, my son&#39;s behaviour has improved noticeably and I am very grateful for his work. I would happily recommend his services to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;parent-of-a-9-year-old-2000&#34;&gt;Parent of a 9 year old, 2000&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn..Shawn.. Shawn.., Thank you SO much for all your magic – I know that [my son] has worked on this himself but we couldn&#39;t have done it without you – so huge thanks. He is a joy to be with now and long may it continue!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hellen-from-west-vancouver-2012&#34;&gt;Hellen from West Vancouver, 2012&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within weeks of her first sessions with Shawn, our daughter was more confident and relaxed than we had ever seen her. Physical and emotional symptoms of anxiety began to subtly, but steadily melt away. We just couldn&#39;t be happier. Thanks Shawn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;adam-and-susan-and-our-son-thomas-2016&#34;&gt;Adam and Susan, and our son, Thomas. 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we like most about Shawn&#39;s approach is that our child is receiving all the therapeutic attention without feeling like the&#39;s in therapy. Shawn has done an excellent job of creating a positive environment where our son can feel safe and continue to flourish.  Shawn has been tremendous and our child loves being around him. It&#39;s been nothing short of positive for us.
Thank you, immensely!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
